This was in an area called Wellawatta, a prime residential area in Colombo.
كان هذا في منطقة تسمى ويلاواتا، و هي منطقة سكنية رئيسية في كولومبو
We stood on the railroad tracks
وقفنا على السكك الحديدية
that ran between my friend's house and the beach.
التي تمر بين بيت صديقي و الشاطئ
The tracks are elevated about eight feet from the waterline normally,
عادة تكون المسارات مرتفعة حوالى 8 أقدام عن مستوى المياه
but at that point the water had receded
و لكن المياه قد انحسرت في تلك اللحظة
to a level three or four feet below normal.
إلى مستوى 3 أو 4 أقدام أقل عن المعتاد
I'd never seen the reef here before.
لم أر الشعاب المرجانية هنا من قبل
There were fish caught in rock pools left behind by the receding water.
كانت هناك أسماك عالقة في برك صخرية خلفها انحسار المياه
Some children jumped down and ran to the rock pools with bags.
قفز بعض الأطفال و جروا ناحيتها حاملين أكياساً
They were trying to catch fish.
كانوا يحاولون صيد الأسماك
No one realized that this was a very bad idea.
لم يدرك أحد بأن هذه كانت فكرة سيئة للغاية
The people on the tracks just continued to watch them.
و استمر الناس على السكك في مراقبتهم
I turned around to check on my friend's house.
التفت إلى الخلف للاطمئنان على منزل صديقي.
Then someone on the tracks screamed.
ثم صرخ أحد الواقفين على السكك!
Before I could turn around, everyone on the tracks was screaming and running.
قبل أن التفت، كل من كان حولي بدأ بالصراخ و الهروب.
The water had started coming back. It was foaming over the reef.
بدأت المياه بالعودة و غطت الرغوة الشعاب المرجانية
The children managed to run back onto the tracks.
تمكن الأطفال من الرجوع إلى السكك الحديدية
No one was lost there. But the water continued to climb.
لم يفقد أحد هناك و لكن استمرت المياه بالتصاعد
In about two minutes, it had reached the level of the railroad tracks
و قد وصلت إلى مستوى السكك في خلال دقيقتين
and was coming over it. We had run about 100 meters by this time.
و بدأت تغطيها، في تلك الاثناء كنا قد ركضنا حوالي 100 متر
It continued to rise.
وإستمريت في الصعود.
I saw an old man standing at his gate, knee-deep in water, refusing to move.
رأيت رجلاً كبيراً في السن يقف أمام بوابة منزله رافضاً الحراك حيث وصل مستوى الماء إلى ركبتيه
He said he'd lived his whole life there by the beach,
قال أنه عاش طوال حياته بالقرب من الشاطئ
and that he would rather die there than run.
و أنه يفضل الموت هناك على الهروب
A boy broke away from his mother to run back into his house
ابتعد صبي عن والدته ليعود مسرعاً إلى البيت
to get his dog, who was apparently afraid.
ليجلب كلبه الذي كان خائفاً بشكل واضح
An old lady, crying, was carried out of her house and up the road by her son.
إمرأة مسنة, تبكي حملها إبنها إلى خارج منزلها إلى الطريق
The slum built on the railroad reservation
الحي الفقير الذي بني في مقاطعة سكة الحديد
between the sea and the railroad tracks was completely swept away.
الذي يقع بين البحر و خطوط السكك الحديدية قد دمر تماماً
Since this was a high-risk location, the police had warned the residents,
و بما أنها منطقة ذات خطورة عالية فقد حذرت الشرطة القاطنين فيها
and no one was there when the water rose.
و لم يكن هناك أحد حين ارتفع مستوى المياه
But they had not had any time to evacuate any belongings.
و لكن لم يكن لديهم الوقت الكافي لإخلاء متعلقاتهم
For hours afterwards, the sea was strewn with bits of wood for miles around --
و تناثرت قطع الخشب على مدى أميال في البحر لعدة ساعات بعد ذلك
all of this was from the houses in the slum.
و كل هذا أتى من البيوت في الأحياء الفقيرة
When the waters subsided, it was as if it had never existed.
و عندما انحسرت المياه، كانت كما أنها لم تكن موجودة
This may seem hard to believe --
ربما يبدو هذا صعب على التصديق
unless you've been reading lots and lots of news reports --
إلا إذا كنت تقرأ العديد من التقارير الأخبارية
but in many places, after the tsunami, villagers were still terrified.
و لكن لازال القرويون في عدة مناطق خائفون من بعد كارثة التسونامي
When what was a tranquil sea swallows up people, homes
منذ اخذ البحر الذي كان هادئا, يبتلع البيوت والناس
and long-tail boats -- mercilessly, without warning --
والمراكب الطويلة بدون رحمة وعلى حين غرة
and no one can tell you anything reliable about whether another one is coming,
و لم يكن باستطاعة أحد أن يجزم بقدوم موجة اخرى
I'm not sure you'd want to calm down either.
لست متأكداً إذا كنت ستهدأ أيضاً
One of the scariest things about the tsunami
أحد الأشياء المخيفة في كارثة التسونامي
that I've not seen mentioned is the complete lack of information.
التي لم يتم ذكرها هو الغياب التام للمعلومات
This may seem minor, but it is terrifying to hear rumor after rumor
هذا قد يبدو بسيطاً و لكنه مخيف عندما تسمع أشاعة بعد أشاعة
after rumor that another tidal wave, bigger than the last,
بعد أشاعة، بأن هناك موجة مد أخرى أكبر من التي سبقتها
will be coming at exactly 1 p.m., or perhaps tonight, or perhaps ...
ستصل الساعة 1 ظهراً أو ربما الليلة أو ربما...
You don't even know if it is safe to go back down to the water,
فانت لا تعلم إذا كانت العودة إلى المياه يبدو أمراً آمناً
to catch a boat to the hospital.
لنستقل المركب لنقلنا إلى المستشفى
We think that Phi Phi hospital was destroyed.
نعتقد أن مستشفى فاي فاي قد دمر
We think this boat is going to Phuket hospital,
لذا تعتقد بأن هذا المركب متجه إلى مستشفى بوكيت
but if it's too dangerous to land at its pier,
و لكن إذا كان الوضع خطيراً جداً للرصف في مينائه
then perhaps it will go to Krabi instead, which is more protected.
ربما سيتجه إلى كرابي الذي يعتبر أكثر أمناً
We don't think another wave is coming right away.
لا نظن أن هناك موجة أخرى قادمة في الحال
At the Phi Phi Hill Resort,
في منتجع فاي فاي هيل
I was tucked into the corner furthest away from the television,
كنت منطوياً في أبعد زاوية و بعيداً عن التلفزيون
but I strained to listen for information.
ولكني كنت استمع بتوتر للحصول على معلومات
They reported that there was an 8.5 magnitude earthquake in Sumatra,
لقد أفادوا بتعرض جزيرة سومطرة لهزة أرضية بقوة 8.5 درجات على مقياس ريختر
which triggered the massive tsunami.
التي تسببت في موجات المد العاتية
Having this news was comforting in some small way
كان ذلك الخبر مريحاً بعض الشيء
to understand what had just happened to us.
لنفهم ما قد حصل لنا الآن
However, the report focused on what had already occurred
و مع ذلك ركز التقرير على ما حدث في الواقع
and offered no information on what to expect now.
و لم يقدم أي معلومات عن ما يتوقع حدوثه الآن
In general, everything was merely hearsay and rumor,
بشكل عام، كل شيء كان مجرد إشاعات و أقاويل
and not a single person I spoke to for over 36 hours
و لا يوجد أي شخص من الذين تحدثت معهم منذ أكثر من 36 ساعة
knew anything with any certainty.
يمكن أن يعلم أي شيء بالتأكيد
Those were two accounts of the Asian tsunami from two Internet blogs
كان هذان موقفان من كارثة التسونامي التي حصلت في آسيا من مدونتين إلكترونيتين
that essentially sprang up after it occurred.
التي انتشرت أساساً بكثرة بعد حدوثها
I'm now going to show you two video segments from the tsunami
و الآن سأريكم مقطعين من الفيديو من حادثة التسونامي
that also were shown on blogs.
و التي عرضت أيضا في المدونات الإلكترونية
I should warn you, they're pretty powerful.
يجب على أن أحذركم فالمقاطع مؤثرة جداً
One from Thailand, and the second one from Phuket as well.
الأولى من تايلند و الثانية من جزيرة فوكت كذلك
(Screaming)
(صراخ)
Voice 1: It's coming in. It's coming again.
الصوت الأول: أنها قادمة.. أنها قادمة من جديد
Voice 2: It's coming again?
الصوت الثاني: لقد عادت من جديد؟
Voice 1: Yeah. It's coming again.
الصوت الأول: نعم إنها عائدة من جديد
Voice 2: Come get inside here.
الصوت الثاني: (غير واضح)
Voice 1: It's coming again. Voice 2: New wave?
الصوت الأول: إنها قادمة مرة أخرى. موجة جديدة
Voice 1: It's coming again. New wave!
أنها قادمة مرة أخرى
[Unclear]
(غير واضح)
(Screaming)
(صراخ)
They called me out here.
لقد استدعوني هنا
James Surowiecki: Phew. Those were both on this site: waveofdestruction.org.
جايمس سورويكي: كانت هاتان من موقع waveofdistruction.org
In the world of blogs, there's going to be before the tsunami and after the tsunami,
سيكون هناك ما قبل التسونامي و ما بعد التسونامي في عالم المدونات الإلكترونية
because one of the things that happened in the wake of the tsunami was that,
لأن أحد الأشياء التي حصلت في أعقاب كارثة التسونامي هي أن
although initially -- that is, in that first day --
بالرغم كبداية – و هو، من اليوم الأول --
there was actually a kind of dearth of live reporting, there was a dearth of live video
في الواقع كانت هناك ندرة في التقارير المباشرة، كما كانت هناك ندرة في التغطية الحية --
and some people complained about this.
و قد اشتكى البعض من ذلك
They said, "The blogsters let us down."
و قالوا أن المدونين، كما تعلمون، خيبوا آمالهم نوعاً ما
What became very clear was that,
و ما أصبح واضحاً هو أنه
within a few days, the outpouring of information was immense,
في غضون أيام من تدفق المعلومات أصبح هائلا
and we got a complete and powerful picture of what had happened
أصبح لدينا صورة واضحة و قوية لما قد حدث
in a way that we never had been able to get before.
بطريقة لم نكن لنتمكن منها من قبل
And what you had was a group of essentially unorganized, unconnected
و ما كان لديكم من الأساس هي مجموعة غير منظمة و متصلة
writers, video bloggers, etc., who were able to come up with
من الكتاب و المدونون بالفيديو و آخرون الذين تمكنوا من الوصول إلى
a collective portrait of a disaster that gave us a much better sense
صورة مشتركة للكارثة و التي أعطتنا إحساسا أفضل بكثير
of what it was like to actually be there than the mainstream media could give us.
بما كان عليه الحال لمن شهد الواقعة بالفعل, أكثر مما أعطته وسائل الإعلام الرئيسية
And so in some ways the tsunami can be seen as a sort of seminal moment,
و بطريقة ما يمكننا رؤية التسونامي كلحظة مؤثرة
a moment in which the blogosphere came, to a certain degree, of age.
اللحظة التي وصلت فيها المدونات الإلكترونية إلى نقطة معينة من النضوج.
Now, I'm going to move now from this kind of --
الآن سأقوم بالانتقال نوعاً ما من
the sublime in the traditional sense of the word,
من السمو بكل المعنى التقليدي للكلمة
that is to say, awe-inspiring, terrifying -- to the somewhat more mundane.
و هو المذهل و المخيف – إلى المعنى العادي نوعاً ما
Because when we think about blogs,
لأننا عندما نفكر في المدونات الإلكترونية
I think for most of us who are concerned about them,
أعتقد أن معظمنا ممن هم مهتمين به
we're primarily concerned with things like politics, technology, etc.
فنحن نهتم بشكل رئيسي بأشياء مثل السياسة، التكنولوجيا و ما إلى ذلك
And I want to ask three questions in this talk,
و أريد أن أطرح ثلالة أسئلة خلال هذا العرض
in the 10 minutes that remain, about the blogosphere.
خلال العشر دقائق القادمة، بخصوص المدونات االإلكترونية
The first one is, What does it tell us about our ideas,
الأول هو ماذا قد يخبرنا هذا عن أفكارنا
about what motivates people to do things?
و ما قد يحفز الناس لفعل الأشياء؟
The second is, Do blogs genuinely have the possibility
و الثاني هو، هل للمدونات الإمكانية
of accessing a kind of collective intelligence
من الوصول إلى نوع من الفهم المشترك
that has previously remained, for the most part, untapped?
و التي بقيت، كجزء كبير، غير مستغل؟
And then the third part is, What are the potential problems,
و بعد ذلك في الجزء الثالث، ما هي الصعوبات المحتملة
or the dark side of blogs as we know them?
أو الجزء المظلم من المدونات الإلكترونية كما نعرفها؟
OK, the first question:
حسناً، السؤال الأول:
What do they tell us about why people do things?
ماذا قد تخبرنا عن سبب قيام الناس بما يفعلون؟
One of the fascinating things about the blogosphere specifically,
أحد الأشياء المذهلة حول المدونات الإلكترونية بالتحديد
and, of course, the Internet more generally --
و بالطبع الإنترنت بشكل عام
and it's going to seem like a very obvious point,
و قد يبدو كنقطة واضحة جداً
but I think it is an important one to think about --
و لكنني أعتقد بأنه شيء مهم لنفهمه
is that the people who are generating these enormous reams of content
هو أن الأشخاص الذين ينتجون هذا الكم الهائل من المضمون
every day, who are spending enormous amounts of time organizing,
كل يوم، و الذين يقضون أوقات طويلة من التنظيم
linking, commenting on the substance of the Internet,
و التوصيل و التعليق على محتوى الإنترنت
are doing so primarily for free.
يفعلون هذا أساساً دون مقابل
They are not getting paid for it in any way other than in the attention and,
أنهم لا يتقاضون أجراً بأي شكل من الأشكال إلا من خلال الاهتمام و
to some extent, the reputational capital that they gain from doing a good job.
لحد ما، أساس السمعة التي حصلوا عليها مقابل قيامهم بعمل جيد
And this is -- at least, to a traditional economist -- somewhat remarkable,
و هذا، لمختص بالإقتصاد على الأقل، نوعاً ما مبهر
because the traditional account of economic man would say that,
لأن نوعاً ما التفسير التقليدي لشخص اقتصادي سيقول
basically, you do things for a concrete reward, primarily financial.
كما تعلمون، أساساً، تفعلون أشياء مقابل مكافأة، مالية في المقام الأول
But instead, what we're finding on the Internet --
و لكن بدلاً من ذلك ما نعثر عليه في الإنترنت
and one of the great geniuses of it -- is that people have found a way
و أحد الأشياء العبقرية حول هذا الموضوع -- هو أن الناس توصلوا إلى طريقة
to work together without any money involved at all.
للعمل مع بعضهم البعض دون أي تدخل مالي.
They have come up with, in a sense, a different method for organizing activity.
لقد توصلوا، إلى حد ما، لطريقة مختلفة لتنظيم النشاط
The Yale Law professor Yochai Benkler, in an essay called "Coase's Penguin,"
مقالة "بطاريق كوس" لبرفسور القانون في جامعة ييل يوكاي بنكلر
talks about this open-source model, which we're familiar with from Linux,
يتحدث عن هذا، نموذج المصدر المفتوح نوعاً ما، الذي نعرفه من نظام لينكس
as being potentially applicable in a whole host of situations.
بأنها يحتمل أن تكون قابلة للتطبيق في مجموعة من الحالات
And, you know, if you think about this with the tsunami,
و كما تعلمون أن تأملنا هذا الأمر مع كارثة التسونامي
what you have is essentially a kind of an army of local journalists,
ما لديك من الأساس هو حشد غفير من الصحفيين المحليين
who are producing enormous amounts of material
و الذين نوعاً ما ينتجون كميات هائلة من المواد
for no reason other than to tell their stories.
لا لسبب معين إلا أن يحكوا قصصهم
That's a very powerful idea, and it's a very powerful reality.
هذه فكرة قوية جداً و واقع قوي جداً
And it's one that offers really interesting possibilities
و هو حقاً الشيء الذي يقدم إمكانيات مثيرة للاهتمام
for organizing a whole host of activities down the road.
لتنظيم مجموعة كاملة من الأنشطة مع الوقت
So, I think the first thing that the blogosphere tells us
لذا أعتقد بأن الشيء الأول الذي تحدثنا عنه المدونات الإلكترونية
is that we need to expand our idea of what counts as rational,
هو بأننا بحاجة إلى توسيع فهمنا لما قد يعتبر منطقياً
and we need to expand our simple equation of value equals money,
كما أننا بحاجة إلى توسيع معادلتنا البسيطة في أن القيمة تساوي المال
or, you have to pay for it to be good,
أو يجب دفع ثمن ما هو جيد
but that in fact you can end up with collectively really brilliant products
و لكن هذا في الحقيقة يؤدي إلى مجموعة من منتجات رائعة جداً
without any money at all changing hands.
دون مقابل مادي على الإطلاق
There are a few bloggers -- somewhere maybe around 20, now --
هناك عدة مدونون -- ربما حوالي 20 الآن --
who do, in fact, make some kind of money, and a few
ممن يجنون المال في الحقيقة، و قليل
who are actually trying to make a full-time living out of it,
ممن يحاولون أن يجعلوا منه مصدر دخل رئيسي
but the vast majority of them are doing it because they love it
و لكن الغالبية العظمى منهم من يفعل ذلك لحبهم له
or they love the attention, or whatever it is.
أو حبهم للإهتمام أو ما إلى ذلك
So, Howard Rheingold has written a lot about this
فكما تعلمون، هاورد راينجولد كتب الكثير عن هذا الموضوع
and, I think, is writing about this more,
و أعتقد أنه يكتب أكثر عنه
but this notion of voluntary cooperation
و لكن هذا المفهوم من التعاون التطوعي
is an incredibly powerful one, and one worth thinking about.
هو قوي بدرجة كبيرة و يستحق التفكير به
The second question is, What does the blogosphere actually do for us,
السؤال الثاني، ماذا قد تفعل المدونات لنا
in terms of accessing collective intelligence?
من ناحية الوصول إلى فهم مشترك؟
You know, as Chris mentioned, I wrote a book called "The Wisdom of Crowds."
كما تعلمون، كما ذكر كريس، لقد ألفت كتاب بعنوان "حكمة الجماهير"
And the premise of "The Wisdom of Crowds" is that,
و المبدأ من "حكمة الجماهير" هو أنه
under the right conditions, groups can be remarkably intelligent.
في ظل الظروف المناسبة، يمكن للجماعات أن تكون ذكية بشكل ملحوظ
And they can actually often be smarter
و في الواقع بإمكانهم أن يكونوا أذكى
than even the smartest person within them.
حتى من أذكى شخص متواجد بينهم
The simplest example of this is if you ask a group of people
و أبسط مثال لهذا هو أنك إذا سألت مجموعة من الناس
to do something like guess how many jellybeans are in a jar.
لفعل شيء مثل، تخمين عدد حبات الهلام في الجرة
If I had a jar of jellybeans
كما تعلمون، إذ كان بحوزتي جرة حبات الهلام
and I asked you all to guess how many jellybeans were in that jar,
و طلبت منكم تخمين عدد حبات الهلام الموجودة في الجرة
your average guess would be remarkably good.
فإن متوسط تخمينكم سيكون جيدا بشكل ملحوظ
It would be somewhere probably within three and five percent
سيكون بين حوالي 3 و 5 بالمئة
of the number of beans in the jar,
من عدد الحبات الموجودة بالجرة
and it would be better than 90 to 95 percent of you.
و سيكون أفضل من 90 إلى 95 بالمئة منكم
There may be one or two of you who are brilliant jelly bean guessers,
قد يكون هناك شخص أو شخصين بارعين في تخمين عدد حبات الهلام
but for the most part the group's guess
و لكن بالنسبة للجزء الأكبر من تخمين المجموعة
would be better than just about all of you.
سيكون أفضل منكم ككل
And what's fascinating is that you can see this phenomenon at work
و المدهش في هذا الأمر هو أنه بمقدرتكم رؤية هذه الظاهرة في مكان العمل
in many more complicated situations.
في العديد من المجالات الأكثر تعقيداً
For instance, if you look at the odds on horses at a racetrack,
فمثلا إذا نظرت إلى احتمالات فوز الأحصنة في مضمار السباق
they predict almost perfectly how likely a horse is to win.
فإنها تقريباً تتنبأ تماماً مدى احتمالية فوز الحصان
In a sense, the group of betters at the racetrack
أي بمعنى، المجموعة الأفضل في تخمين فرص الفوز في المضمار
is forecasting the future, in probabilistic terms.
تتنبأ بالمستقبل، من حيث الاحتمالات
You know, if you think about something like Google,
كما تعلمون، إذا فكرت ملياً بشيء مثل جوجل
which essentially is relying on the collective intelligence of the Web
الذي يعتمد من الأساس على الفهم المشترك للشبكة
to seek out those sites that have the most valuable information --
للبحث عن تلك المواقع التي تحتوي على أهم المعلومات
we know that Google does an exceptionally good job of doing that,
فإننا نعلم بأن جوجل تعمل بشكل جيد على نحو استثنائي
and it does that because, collectively, this disorganized thing
و هو يفعل ذلك بسبب، و بشكل جماعي، هذا الشيء غير المنظم
we call the "World Wide Web" actually has a remarkable order,
الذي نسميه بشبكة الانترنت لديه نظام رائع
or a remarkable intelligence in it.
أو ذكاء ملحوظ ,في داخله.
And this, I think, is one of the real promises of the blogosphere.
و أعتقد أن هذا بشير النجاح الحقيقي للمدونات الإلكترونية
Dan Gillmor -- whose book "We the Media"
دان جيلمور الذي كتب "نحن، وسائل الإعلام"
is included in the gift pack --
و التي هي من ضمن حقيبة الهدايا
has talked about it as saying that, as a writer,
يتكلم عن هذا الأمر قائلاً أنه ككاتب
he's recognized that his readers know more than he does.
قد علم أن قراؤه يعلمون أكثر منه
And this is a very challenging idea. It's a very challenging idea
و هذه فكرة صعبة جداً، أنها صعبة جداً
to mainstream media. It's a very challenging idea to anyone
لوسائل الإعلام الرئيسية، أنها فكرة صعبة للغاية على أي شخص
who has invested an enormous amount of time and expertise,
استثمر جزء كبير من وقته و خبرته
and who has a lot of energy invested in the notion
و لديه طاقة كبيرة مستثمرة في فكرة
that he or she knows better than everyone else.
أنه أو أنها تعلم أكثر من أي شخص آخر
But what the blogosphere offers is the possibility
و لكن ما تقدمه المدونات الإلكنرونية هو إمكانية
of getting at the kind of collective, distributive intelligence that is out there,
الحصول على هذا النوع من الفهم المشترك و الإفرادي الموجود حولنا
and that we know is available to us
و الذي نعلم أنه متوفر لنا
if we can just figure out a way of accessing it.
إذا حاولنا فقط معرفة الطريقة للوصول إليه
Each blog post, each blog commentary
كل تدوينة و كل تعليق على مدونة
may not, in and of itself, be exactly what we're looking for,
قد لا يكون ما نبحث عنه بحد ذاته
but collectively the judgment of those people posting, those people linking,
و لكن بشكل مشترك، كل آراء الأشخاص الذين يدونون و يتواصلون
more often than not is going to give you a very interesting
في أغلب الأحيان سيعطيك صورة مثيرة للاهتمام
and enormously valuable picture of what's going on.
و قيمة جداً للأحداث التي تجري من حولنا
So, that's the positive side of it.
لذا فإن ذلك هو الجانب الإيجابي منه
That's the positive side of what is sometimes called
إنه الجانب الإيجابي لما قد يسمى أحياناً
participatory journalism or citizen journalism, etc. --
الصحافة المشتركة أو صحافة المواطن و هلم جرا
that, in fact, we are giving people
و في الواقع نحن نعطي الناس
who have never been able to talk before a voice,
الذين لم تكن لديهم المقدرة على التحدث من قبل نوعاً من الصوت
and we're able to access information that has always been there
و لدينا الإمكانية من الوصول لمعلومات لطالما كانت موجودة
but has essentially gone untapped.
و لكن كانت غير ملموسة من الأساس
But there is a dark side to this,
و لكن هناك جانب مظلم لهذا
and that's what I want to spend the last part of my talk on.
و هذا ما أريد أن أتحدث عنه في الجزء الأخير من حديثي
One of the things that happens if you spend a lot of time on the Internet,
أحد الأشياء التي تحصل إذا قضيت وقتاً طويلاً على الانترنت
and you spend a lot of time thinking about the Internet,
و قضيت وقتاً طويلاً في التفكير بالانترنت
is that it is very easy to fall in love with the Internet.
هو أنه من السهل الوقوع في الحب مع شبكة الانترنت
It is very easy to fall in love with the decentralized,
من السهل أن تقع في حب البنية اللامركزية
bottom-up structure of the Internet.
و العكسية للانترنت
It is very easy to think that networks are necessarily good things --
و من السهل أن تعتقد بأن الشبكات بالضرورة أمور جيدة
that being linked from one place to another,
و أن كونك متصل من مكان لآخر
that being tightly linked in a group, is a very good thing.
و كونك متصل بشكل مقرب بمجموعة هو أمر جيد
And much of the time it is.
و في الغالب هو كذلك
But there's also a downside to this -- a kind of dark side, in fact --
و لكن هناك جانب سلبي لهذا أيضاُ – في الواقع جانب مظلم نوعاً ما
and that is that the more tightly linked we've become to each other,
و هو أن كلما كان الترابط محكم بيننا
the harder it is for each of us to remain independent.
كلما صعب علينا أن نبقى مستقلين
One of the fundamental characteristics of a network is that,
أحد الصفات الأساسية للشبكة هي أن
once you are linked in the network,
بمجرد أن تكون متصلاً بالشبكة
the network starts to shape your views
فتبدأ الشبكة في تشكيل وجهات نظرك
and starts to shape your interactions with everybody else.
كما تبدأ بتشكيل تفاعلك مع الآخرين
That's one of the things that defines what a network is.
و هذا أحد الأشياء الذي يوضح ما هي الشبكة
A network is not just the product of its component parts.
فالشبكة ليست نتاج الأجزاء المكونة لها
It is something more than that.
أنه شيء أكثر بكثير من هذا
It is, as Steven Johnson has talked about, an emergent phenomenon.
أنه و كما تحدث عنه ستيفن جونسون، ظاهرة مستحدثة
Now, this has all these benefits:
و الآن، هذا الأمر لديه كل هذه الفوائد
it's very beneficial in terms of the efficiency of communicating information;
أنه مفيد من حيث الكفاءة في نقل المعلومات
it gives you access to a whole host of people;
أنه يعطي المجال للوصول إلى مجموعة كاملة من الناس
it allows people to coordinate their activities in very good ways.
كما يسمح للناس من تنسيق نشاطاتهم بطرق جيدة
But the problem is that groups are only smart
و لكن المشكلة هي أن الجماعات تكون ذكية فقط
when the people in them are as independent as possible.
إذا كانوا أفرادها مستقلين قدر الإمكان
This is the paradox of the wisdom of crowds,
و هذا هو نوعاً ما النقيض لـ"حكمة الجماهير"
or the paradox of collective intelligence,
أو النقيض للفهم المشترك
that what it requires is actually a form of independent thinking.
و الذي يتطلب في الواقع نوع من التفكير المستقل
And networks make it harder for people to do that,
و الشبكات تصعب على الناس فعل ذلك
because they drive attention to the things that the network values.
لأنه يدفع بالاهتمام إلى الأشياء التي تهتم بها الشبكة
So, one of the phenomena that's very clear in the blogosphere
لذا أحد الظواهر الواضحة في المدونات الإلكترونية
is that once a meme, once an idea gets going,
حالما تبدأ فكرة أو جزء قابل للانتقال عبر الانترنت
it is very easy for people to just sort of pile on,
من السهل على الناس أن يتمركزوا فيه
because other people have, say, a link.
لأن لدى أشخاص آخرون، مثلاً، رابط
People have linked to it, and so other people in turn link to it, etc., etc.
متصل به أشخاص آخرون و في المقابل هناك أشحاص آخرون متصلين بهم و هلم جرا
And that phenomenon
و هذه الظاهرة، هذه الظاهرة
of piling on the existing links
لنوع من التمركز على الروابط القائمة
is one that is characteristic of the blogosphere,
هي أحد صفات المدونات الإلكترونية
particularly of the political blogosphere,
و بالأخص المدونات السياسية
and it is one that essentially throws off
و هي من الاساس تحتوي على
this beautiful, decentralized, bottom-up intelligence
هذا النوع من الإدراك اللامركزي و العكسي
that blogs can manifest in the right conditions.
الذي يبرز المدونات في الموقع المناسب
The metaphor that I like to use is the metaphor of the circular mill.
و التشبيه الذي أود أن أستعمله هو التشبيه بالطاحونة الدائرية
A lot of people talk about ants.
الكثير من الناس تتحدث عن النمل
You know, this is a conference inspired by nature.
كما تعلمون، هذا مؤتمر مستوحاه من الطبيعة
When we talk about bottom-up, decentralized phenomena,
عندما نتحدث عن ظاهرة عكسية و لامركزية
the ant colony is the classic metaphor, because,
فإن مستعمرة النمل هو التشبيه المتوقع له، لأن، كما تعلمون
no individual ant knows what it's doing,
ليست للنملة أي إدراك لما تفعله
but collectively ants are able to reach incredibly intelligent decisions.
و لكن بشكل جماعي فللنمل أن يتوصل إلى قرارات ذكية بشكل لا يصدق
They're able to reach food as efficiently as possible,
فهي لها الإمكانية لتوجيه حركة مرورها بسرعة ملحوظة
So, the ant colony is a great model:
لذا فإن مستعمرة النمل يعتبر نموذجاً رائعاً
you have all these little parts that collectively add up to a great thing.
فلديكم كل هذه الأجزاء الصغيرة التي اجتمعت لتصبح شيئاً رائعا
But we know that occasionally ants go astray,
و لكن نحن نعلم بأن النمل قد بضل طريقه في بعض الأحيان
and what happens is that, if army ants are wandering around and they get lost,
و ما يحصل هو أنه إذا كان عدد كبير من النمل يتجول نوعاً ما و يضل طريقه
they start to follow a simple rule --
فيبدأون باتباع قاعدة بسيطة --
just do what the ant in front of you does.
فقط اتبع ما تفعله النملة التي أمامك
And what happens is that the ants eventually end up in a circle.
و هذا ما يحصل و هو أن النمل انتهى به المطاف و هو يسير في دائرة
And there's this famous example of one that was 1,200 feet long
و هناك مثال شهير لطابور من النمل طوله 1,200 قدم
and lasted for two days, and the ants just kept marching around and around
و استمرت لمدة يومين، و استمر النمل بالسير حول نفسها
in a circle until they died.
في دائرة حتى ماتت
And that, I think, is a sort of thing to watch out for.
و ذلك كما أعتقد هو ما يجب ما أن نتطلع إليه
That's the thing we have to fear --
و هذا هو الشيء الذي يجب ان نخاف منه
is that we're just going to keep marching around and around until we die.
و هو أن نسير في دوامة إلى أن نموت
Now, I want to connect this back, though, to the tsunami,
الآن أود أن أربط هذا بالتسونامي
because one of the great things about the tsunami --
لأن أحد الأشياء العظيمة عن التسونامي --
in terms of the blogosphere's coverage,
من حيث تغطية المدونات الإلكترونية
not in terms of the tsunami itself --
و ليس من ناحية التسونامي نفسه--
is that it really did represent a genuine bottom-up phenomenon.
هو أنه في الحقيقة مثل الظاهرة العكسية
You saw sites that had never existed before getting huge amounts of traffic.
لقد رأيتم مواقع لم تكن موجودة من قبل ,تتلقى عدد هائل من الزوار
You saw people being able to offer up their independent points of view
كما رأيتم أشخاصا لديهم الإمكانية للتعبير عن وجهات نظرهم المستقلة
in a way that they hadn't before.
بطريقة لم تكن باستطاعهم من قبل
There, you really did see the intelligence of the Web manifest itself.
و هنا رأيتم بالفعل ذكاء الشبكة فى أبهى حالاته
So, that's the upside. The circular mill is the downside.
إذا فهذا هو الجانب الإيجابي. و الطاحونة الدائرية هي الجانب السلبي.
And I think that the former is what we really need to strive for.
و أعتقد أن الأسبق هو ما يجب علينا أن نكافح من أجله
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكراً جزيلاً